Chapter 8. Schools and school masters.
The previous chapter gave account of an immense body or herd of sperm whales,
and there was also then given the probable cause inducing those vast aggregations.
Now, though such great bodies are at times encountered, yet as must have been
seen, even at the present day, small detached bands are occasionally
observed, embracing from 20 to 50 individuals each. Such bands are known
as schools. They generally are of two sorts. Those composed almost entirely of
females and those mustering none but young vigorous males or bulls as they
are familiarly designated.
In cavalier attendance upon the school of females, you invariably see a male of
fullgrown magnitude, but not old, who upon any alarmces his gallantry by
falling in the rear and covering the flight of his ladies. In truth, this
gentleman is a luxurious ottoman, swimming about over the watery world,
surroundingly accompanied by all the solices and endearments of the herum.
The contrast between this Ottoman and his concubines is striking, because
while he is always of the largest Leviathanic proportions, the ladies,
even at full growth, are not more than onethird of the bulk of an average size
male. They are comparatively delicate indeed. I dare say not to exceed half a
dozen yards round the waist.
Nevertheless, it cannot be denied that upon the whole they are hereditarily entitled to ambom.
It is very curious to watch this herum and its lord in their indolent
ramblings. Like fashionables, they are forever on the move in leisurely search
of variety. You meet them on the line in time for the full flower of the
equatorial feeding season. having just returned perhaps from spending the
summer in the northern seas and so cheating summer of all unpleasant
weariness and warmth by the time they have lounged up and down the prominade
of the equator a while they start for the oriental waters in anticipation of
the cool season there and so evade the other excessive temperature of the year
when serenely advancing on one of these journeys if any strange suspicious
sights are seen my lord whale keeps keeps a weary eye on his interesting
family. Should any unwarrantably per young Leviathan coming that way presume
to draw confidentially close to one of the ladies, with what prodigious fury
the Bashaw assails him and chases him away. High times indeed. If unprincipled
young rakes like him are to be permitted to invade the sanctity of domestic
bliss, though do what the Bashaw will, he cannot keep the most notorious
lethario out of his bed, for alas all fish bed in common. As a shore, the
ladies often cause the most terrible jewels among their rival admirers, just
so with the whales, who sometimes come to deadly battle and all for love. They
fence with their long lower jaws, sometimes locking them together, and so
striving for the supremacy like elks that waringly interweave their antlers.
Not a few are captured, having deep scars of these encounters, furrowed
heads, broken teeth, scalloped fins, and in some instances wrenched and dislocated mouths.
But supposing the invader of domestic bliss to be take himself away at the
first rush of the Herams lord, then it is very diverting to watch that lord.
Gently he insinuates his vast bulk among them again, and revels there a while,
still in tantalizing vicinity to young lethario, like pious Solomon devoutly
worshiping among his thousand concubines.
granting other whales to be in sight.
The fishermen will seldom give chase to one of these grand Turks, for these
grand Turks are too lavish of their strength, and hence their anxiousness is
small. As for the sons and daughters they beget, why those sons and daughters
must take care of themselves, at least with only the maternal help. For like
certain other omnivorous roving lovers that might be named, my lord Whale has
no taste for the nursery, however much for the bower. And so being a great
traveler, he leaves his anonymous babies all over the world, every baby an
exotic. In good time, nevertheless, as the aror of youth declines, as years and
dumps increase, as reflection lends her solemn pauses, in short, as a general
latitude overtakes the sated Turk, then a love of ease and virtue supplants the
love for maidens, our Ottoman enters upon the impotent, repentant, admonatory
stage of life, for swears, disbands the herm, and grown to an exemplary, sulky
old soul, goes about all alone among the meridians and parallels, saying his
prayers and warning each young Leviathan from his amorous errors.
Now, as the herm of Wales is called by the fisherman a school, so is the lord
and master of that school technically known as the school master. It is
therefore not in strict character, however admirably satirical, that after
going to school himself, he should then go abroad, inculcating not what he
learned there, but the folly of it. His title schoolmaster would very naturally
seem derived from the name bestowed upon the herm itself. But some have surmised
that the man who first thus entitled this sort of Ottoman whale must have
read the memoirs of Vidok and informed himself what sort of a country school
master that famous Frenchman was in his younger days, and what was the nature of
those occult lessons he inculcated into some of his pupils.
The same secludedness and isolation to which the school master whale betakes
himself in his advancing years is true of all aged sperm whales. Almost
universally, a lone whale, as a solitary Leviathan is called, proves an ancient
one. Like venerable mossbearded Daniel Boone, he will have no one near him but
nature herself, and her he takes to wife in the wilderness of waters, and the
best of wives she is, though she keeps so many moody secrets.
The schools composing none but young and vigorous males previously mentioned
offer a strong contrast to the herum schools. For while those female whales
are characteristically timid, the young males, or 40 barrel bulls, as they call
them, are by far the most pugnacious of all Leviathans, and proverbally the most
dangerous to encounter, excepting those wondrous gay-headed gristled whales
sometimes met. And these will fight you like grim fiends exasperated by a penal gout.
The 40 barrel bull schools are larger than the herm schools. Like a mob of
young collegians, they are full of fight, fun, and wickedness, tumbling
round the world at such a reckless rollicking rate that no prudent
underwriter would ensure them any more than he would a riotous lad at Yale or
Harvard. They soon relinquish this turbulence though and when about three
force grown break up and separately go about in quest of settlements that is harams.
Another point of difference between the male and female schools is still more
characteristic of the sexes. Say you strike a 40 barrel bull. Poor devil all
his comrades quit him. but strike a member of the herm school, and her
companions swim around her with every token of concern, sometimes lingering so
near her and so long as themselves to fall ap Prey.